Guide to the A.M. Rosenthal papers, 1959-2004
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
A.M. Rosenthal papers
1959-2004
MssCol 17930
17930
Rosenthal, A. M. (Abraham Michael), 1922-2006
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
14.55 linear feet 40 boxes
The A.M. Rosenthal papers document the career of New York Times Managing and Executive Editor Abraham Michael Rosenthal (1922-2006), noted for his stewardship of that newspaper during one of its most tumultuous periods, from the 1960s through the 1980s. The collection contains Rosenthal's personal files from the era of his editorial tenure and beyond. The papers include extensive professional correspondence, journals, speeches, subject files, writings, and scrapbooks. They detail Rosenthal's activities and interactions during his years as an editor and a columnist.
A. M. Rosenthal (1922-2006) was a Pulitzer Prize-winning foreign correspondent who became the executive editor of The New York Times and led the paper's global news operations through 17 years of record growth, modernization and major journalistic change. After 19 years as a reporter and correspondent, Rosenthal spent the next 23 years serving successively as metropolitan editor, assistant managing editor, managing editor and executive editor, securing The Times's journalistic significance by pursuing the news aggressively and modernizing the paper while maintaining its strictest standards.
Abraham Michael Rosenthal was born in Sault Ste. Marie, Canada on May 2, 1922, the sixth child of Russian immigrants. The family emigrated to the United States three years later. Growing up in the Bronx during the Great Depression, Abe faced the same poverty as so many of his neighbors, but he had other hardships to endure. His father died when Abe was still very young, as did three of his five sisters. As a teenager, Abe was bedridden for two years by a case of osteomyelitis. Told he would probably never walk again, Abe expected the worst, but help from his surviving sisters allowed him to travel to the Mayo Clinic, where he slowly recovered.
Rosenthal was an eager student, but not a rich one, so he happily attended City College of New York, the academically rigorous, but no-cost, school in Manhattan. Taking particular delight in political discussion there, Rosenthal aspired to the coveted position of The New York Times City College campus correspondent. Attaining the job in his senior year, Rosenthal began a relationship with the paper that continued for over fifty years. He worked on the city staff as a general assignment reporter from his graduation in 1943 until he was named United Nations correspondent in 1945. After nine years covering the U.N., Rosenthal traveled the world as a foreign correspondent, stationed in India, Poland, Switzerland, and Japan from 1954 to 1963. His coverage of the political situation in Poland won him two of his proudest honors: a Pulitzer Prize and forcible expulsion from Poland.
Reluctantly returning to New York, Rosenthal was named Metropolitan Editor (an appellation he disliked, preferring the old title of City Editor). He presided over the expansion of New York coverage, adding more feature stories and social observation to the typical crime beat and press conference summaries common to city desks of the era. In 1967, Rosenthal was promoted to Assistant Managing Editor and, shortly thereafter, to Associate Managing Editor. In 1969, he was named Managing Editor. He took a more hands-on approach to the job than his predecessors, with his first action being to insist on reading selected copy before it appeared in the paper. Rosenthal himself later contrasted his style with that of earlier editors by suggesting that they preferred to be judges, assessing what was good or bad about yesterday's paper, while he preferred to be a participant, guiding what would be in tomorrow's paper.
Rosenthal found ways to enlarge the scope of the paper, adding daily sections on various special subjects, such as business, science, and entertainment. His changes increased circulation and advertising, allowing The New York Times to maintain its profitability as more people turned to television for their daily news consumption, while broadening the definition of news itself in the "paper of record." By 1976, the Sunday paper, previously a separate editorial entity, merged with the daily paper, and Rosenthal was named Executive Editor, responsible for every page of The New York Times, except for the editorial and Op-Ed pages.
In spite of presiding over an era of unprecedented change, Rosenthal's primary editorial goal was always to "keep the paper straight." Eager to keep any bias out of Times news coverage, Rosenthal constantly reminded his reporters and editors of the importance of impartial journalism. Rosenthal generally felt that as long as the Times received criticism from both sides of the political spectrum on a given issue, the reporting had been fair. Ironically, one of the controversies arising during Rosenthal's tenure resulted from one of the very few pieces he wrote as an editor. He was at Columbia University on the night of a particularly violent student protest in 1968 and, after surveying the aftermath, he decided to write an article covering the story. Critics from within The New York Times, as well as from outside, accused Rosenthal of showing his sympathy for the administration and his contempt for the protesters. He denied any bias, but did avoid any subsequent original reporting. Some controversial policy issues arising during Rosenthal's tenure sprang from stylistic choices; until 1986, "Ms." was not a permissible honorific in the Times and "gay" could only be used as a synonym for happy. On the other side of the political coin, the publication of the Pentagon Papers made The Times, and Rosenthal in particular, a target of conservative criticism.
At the helm of a staff of highly regarded editors and writers that included many young stars he had recruited, Rosenthal directed coverage of the major news stories of the era - the war in Vietnam, the Pentagon Papers, the Watergate scandal and successive crises in the Middle East. After 17 years as a principal architect of the modern New York Times, Rosenthal stepped down as the top editor in 1986, having nearly reached the mandatory retirement age set for the editorial staff of the paper. He then began the last phase of his Times career, nearly 13 years as the author of a twice-weekly column, "On My Mind," for the Op-Ed page. The column centered on public affairs in general, with a particular focus on international issues, human rights, and drug policy in America. After publisher Arthur Ochs Sulzberger, Jr. ended Rosenthal's tenure as a Times columnist in 1999, Rosenthal continued as a columnist with the New York Daily News, as well as with several online media outlets. He made no secret of his disappointment at being asked to leave his lifelong journalistic home, but he was eager to keep writing on the subjects about which he still had something to say.
Rosenthal was married to Ann Marie Burke from 1949 to 1986, and to Shirley Lord from 1987 until his death. He had three sons with his first wife, one of whom, Andrew Rosenthal, went on to become an editor at The New York Times.
The A.M. Rosenthal papers consist of Rosenthal's personal files, spanning his editorial tenure and his subsequent career as a columnist and commentator. The personal series contains those papers kept separately from The New York Times office files. Maintained in Rosenthal's New York home, these files add dimension to the picture of Rosenthal's years as an editor, and also provide a look at his later career as a columnist, finally free to express his own views to the public. They include notes for speeches given by Rosenthal from the 1960s through the early 2000s; subject files for his columns from 1987 through the early 2000s; and some additional correspondence, primarily from 1987 onward, but some earlier letters, as well. Highlights of this series include seventeen journals spanning 1971-1986, containing appointment data and attached correspondence, creating almost a scrapbook for each year; transcripts of an oral history recorded at The New York Times in 1983 and 1985, containing very frank and specific discussions of the events and people at the paper during Rosenthal's career; and some of Rosenthal's own writings, most notably, drafts of various chapters of an unpublished memoir.
While some of the correspondence in these papers dates from the era of Rosenthal's editorship, including some internal New York Times memoranda, the majority comes from the years 1987-2004, when Rosenthal was a columnist for The Times and other publications. There are a few individual correspondent files, most notably one with Richard Nixon, in which the columnist and the former president discuss world affairs of the early 1990s. There are folders designated by Rosenthal as "special letters," some of which come from famous people, whereas others seem to be letters he considered personally significant. Correspondents in this section include statesmen, such as Hubert Humphrey and Daniel Patrick Moynihan, journalists, such as Dan Rather and Barbara Walters, and business leaders, such as Steve Forbes and Donald Trump. Perhaps the most revealing correspondence in the series, however, dates from 1999, when Rosenthal was forcibly retired from The New York Times at the publisher's request. There are hundreds of letters from friends, acquaintances, and readers sent to Rosenthal directly, as well as to The Times, expressing their sorrow and outrage at the decision. There are copies of some of Rosenthal's replies included also, providing a candid view of his own feelings at the time.
Not journals in the conventional sense, Rosenthal's journals are a combination of scrapbooks and diaries. Detailing the years 1971-1986, they illustrate the highlights of most of his tenure as the leading decision maker of The New York Times. They list major appointments and excursions, with related letters and other papers attached where appropriate. The journals provide researchers with a sense not only of how Rosenthal spent his time, but of what he thought was important. There are, in addition, two actual scrapbooks included in the series. Both date from 1959-1960, focusing on Rosenthal's time as a correspondent in Poland. One scrapbook centers on his expulsion by the government as a reaction to the reports he filed, and the other centers on the Pulitzer Prize he won for those same reports.
Rosenthal's years at The Times are reviewed and relived via his official oral history, included in this collection. Times Vice Chairman Sydney Gruson met with Rosenthal for four sessions in 1983 and 1985, and their discussion was transcribed for posterity. Rosenthal shares his memories and views on colleagues and controversies, predecessors and policies. The history seems to have been intended to continue, but the fourth session is the last one included. Researchers interested in Rosenthal's personal history and thoughts will find his memoir drafts worthwhile also. Never published, Rosenthal's memoir exists as various sections and chapters, compiled over many years. He began in the early 1960s, writing about his experiences as a student and a correspondent, and then returned to the project many times throughout the years. There is no complete version of the memoir, but readers can piece together most of Rosenthal's early life and career from the chapters included.
Other writings include a complete list of Rosenthal's columns from 1987-2000, arranged by both subject and date, drafts of news and magazine pieces on Moscow, China, and the Philippines, and a notebook containing some ideas, in Rosenthal's own handwriting, for columns and stories. A typescript of his last column for The New York Times is included, signed by nineteen Times staff members, including Howell Raines and Rosenthal's son, Andrew. Two versions of Rosenthal's will are also found in this series.
Notes and drafts of speeches are arranged chronologically, with venues ranging from clubs, sales conferences, and graduations to private parties, memorial services, and even the U.S. House of Representatives. The speeches span the 1960s through the early 2000s, most of Rosenthal's life as an influential figure in public discourse.
Subject files for columns are arranged alphabetically, containing some correspondence, research notes, and printed matter not necessarily available to the general public. All of the material in the subject files was generated and obtained during Rosenthal's career as a columnist at The New York Times and for other publications.
Rosenthal's life and career before becoming Assistant Managing Editor of The Times are not well-represented in the collection, with only two scrapbooks and part of his memoir touching on those early years.
The A.M. Rosenthal Papers are organized in the following series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1970-2004
Series II: Journals, 1971-1986
Series III: Oral history and photographs, 1978-1985, undated
Series IV: Scrapbooks, 1959-1960
Series V: Speeches, 1968-2000
Series VI: Subject files, 1987-2002
Series VII: Writings, 1961-2000
Purchased from the estate of A.M. Rosenthal, 2009
New York Times Company Records. A.M. Rosenthal Papers. Manuscripts and Archives Division, New York Public Library.
Rosenthal, A. M. (Abraham Michael), 1922-2006; New York Times Company; American newspapers -- New York (State) -- New York; Journalism -- United States -- 20th century; Newspaper publishing -- New York (State) -- New York; Reporters and reporting; New York times; Diaries; Photographs; Scrapbooks; United States -- Politics and government
- Series I: Correspondence, 1970-2004; 379409; 3 boxes
  - Awards, 379410 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book letters, 379411 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Columbia Journalism Review, 379412 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - De la Renta, Oscar, 379413 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Douglas, Peter, 379414 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - India, 379415 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invitations, 379416 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memos from AMR, 379417 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memos to AMR, 379418 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Nixon, Richard, 379419 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal, 1971; 379420 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Retirement from New York Times, 379421
    - 1999, 379422 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
    - 1999-2000, 379423 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Rosenthal sons (Jonathan, Daniel, Andrew), 379424 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Six-Column paper, 379425 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Special letters, 379426 (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
  - Statements (important), 379427 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sulzberger, A.O., 379428 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Thank-you letters (knee operation), 379429 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thirty-Eight Witnesses, 379430 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Unsorted, 1966-2004; 379431 (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
- Series II: Journals, 1971-1986; 379432; 9 boxes
  - 1971-1972, 379433 (Box 4, Volume 1-2)
  - 1973-1974, 379434 (Box 5, Volume 1-2)
  - 1975-1976, 379435 (Box 6, Volume 1-2)
  - 1977-1978, 379436 (Box 7, Volume 1-2)
  - 1979-1980, 379437 (Box 8, Volume 1-2)
  - 1981, 379438 (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - 1982-1983, 379439 (Box 10, Volume 1-2)
  - 1984; 1986, 379440 (Box 11, Volume 1-2)
  - 1985, 379441 (Box 12, Volume 1-2)
- Series III: Oral history and photographs, 1978-1985, undated; 379442; 1 box
  - Oral history transcripts, 1983; 1985; 379443 (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
  - Photographs, 1978, n.d.; 379444 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks, 1959-1960; 379445; 1 box (Box 14, Volume 1-2)
  Poland
- Series V: Speeches, 1968-2000; 379446; 7 boxes
  - Radio/TV appearances, 1968-1978; 379447 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - General, 1971-1973; 379448 (Box 15, Folder 2-4)
  - Testimony before House subcommittee re: Newsmen's Privilege, 1973; 379449 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - General, 1974-1976; 379450 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Journalism and the Law, 1976; 379451 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Ohio University, 1976; 379452 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - New York University School of Law Bicentennial Conference, 1976; 379453 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - General, 1976-1979; 379454 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Judicial conference of the Second Circuit, 1979; 379455 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Florida Press Association, 1980; 379456 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
  - Colby College, 1981; 379457 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Finley Medal, 1981; 379458 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Silurians Award, 1981; 379459 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Joint ABA-ANPA Task Force, 1982; 379460 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - ANPA panel, 1983; 379461 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Turner Catledge memorial, 1983; 379462 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Staff editor meeting, 1983; 379463 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - SUNY Brockport, 1984; 379464 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Art Directors Club Hall of Fame, 1984; 379465 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Town Hall series, Sarasota, 1984; 379466 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - New York By Night, 1985; 379467 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Sigma Delta Chi, Fort Worth, 1986; 379468 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Chancellor's Council of the University of California, 1986; 379469 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - National Association of Black Journalists convention, 1986; 379470 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - New York Times advertising sales conference, 1986; 379471 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Mission Inn sales conference, 1986; 379472 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - National Press Foundation, 1987; 379473 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Meet the Press, 1987; 379474 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Rosenthal award, 1987; 379475 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Max David Journalism Prize, Milan, 1988; 379476 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - New York University, 1988; 379477 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Sutton Place Synagogue, 1988; 379478 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Boston, 1988; 379479 (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Bush speech, 1989; 379480 (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Columbia University, 1989; 379481 (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Cleveland, 1989; 379482 (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - Cincinnati, 1989; 379483 (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - General, 1991; 379484 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Pentagon Papers conference, 1991; 379485 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Los Angeles, 1992; 379486 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Simon Wiesenthal Center, Town Hall, 1992; 379487 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - American Friends of Hebrew University, 1992; 379488 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Malcolm Forbes dedication, Brown University, 1992; 379489 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - New York Academy of Science, 1992; 379490 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Cleveland UJA; Montreal; Norfolk, 1992; 379491 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Federation of Phoenix--Operation Exodus, 1992; 379492 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Middle East Council, 1992; 379493 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Jewish Community Federation of Greater Rochester, 1992; 379494 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Grayson Memorial Lecture, Congregation B'nai Jeshurun, 1992; 379495 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Hebrew Union College [1992}, 379496 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Boston--Anti-Defamation League, 1992; 379497 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - New Jersey Jewish Federation, 1992; 379498 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Central Synagogue, 1993; 379499 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Federation/UJA--Palm Beach, 1993; 379500 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - UJA--Chicago, 1993; 379501 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Bernard Leser tribute, 1993; 379502 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Community Center, West Orange, NJ, 1993; 379503 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - UJA--Milwaukee, 1993; 379504 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Anti-Defamation League, 1994; 379505 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Lotus Club, 1995; 379506 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Women's American ORT, 1995; 379507 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Future of Hope--Hiroshima, 1995; 379508 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - American Bar Association--Palm Beach, 1996; 379509 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - National Council of Jewish Women, 1996; 379510 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - UJA--Wyckoff, NJ, 1996; 379511 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society Award--Grand Hyatt Hotel, 1996; 379512 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - UJA--Louisville, 1996; 379513 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League--Palm Beach, 1997; 379514 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Federation of Waterbury / Temple Beth Shalom, Livingston, NJ, 1997; 379515 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Ben Gurion University, 1997; 379516 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 'Punch' Sulzberger party, 1998; 379517 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - American Society for Technion, 1998; 379518 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - India, 1998; 379519 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Federation--Des Moines, 1998; 379520 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Baltimore Jewish Federation, 1998; 379521 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Pace College, 1998; 379522 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Boston Jewish Federation, 1998; 379523 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Har Zion Temple--Philadelphia, 1999; 379524 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - New Orleans, 1999; 379525 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - General, 2000; 379526 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Journalism, n.d; 379527 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous speeches, n.d.; 379528 (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Subject files, 1987-2002; 379529; 15 boxes
  - Abortion, 379530 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Afghanistan, 379531 (Box 22, Folder 2-3)
  - Africa, 379532 (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
  - AIDS, 379533 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Al Qaeda, 379534 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Albania, 379535 (Box 22, Folder 8-9)
  - Albright, Madeleine, 379536 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - America, 379537 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Amnesty International, 379538 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Anderson, Terry, 379539 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Anti-America, 379540 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Anti-Jews, 379541 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Anti-Semitism, 379542 (Box 22, Folder 16-17)
  - Arab Human development, 379543 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Arab/Israel, 379544 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Arabs, 379545 (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
  - Arafat, Yasir, 379546 (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
  - Argentina, 379547 (Box 23, Folder 7-8)
  - Arms control, 379548 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Atkins, Tommy, 379549 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Austria, 379550 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Awards, 379551 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Baltic, 379552 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Baruch, Bernard, 379553 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Bauer, Gary, 379554 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Blacks, 379555 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Blacks/Farrakhan, 379556 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Blix, Hans, 379557 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Bosnia, 379558 (Box 24, Folder 7-8)
  - Brown, Helen Gurley, 379559 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Brunner, Alois, 379560 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Buchanan, Patrick, 379561 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Buckley, William F., 379562 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Burns, John, 379563 (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
  - Center for Religious Freedom, 379564 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Center for Security Policy, 379565 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Central Intelligence Agency, 379566 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Century Association, 379567 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Chemical weapons, 379568 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - China, 379569 (Box 25, Folder 8-11)
  - China, 379570 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - City College of New York, 379571 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Clinton impeachment, 379572 (Box 26, Folder 3-4)
  - Columbia College--Methadone, 379573 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Concern USA, 379574 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Congress, 379575 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Costa Rica, 379576 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Crime, 379577 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Criminal Court notes, 379578 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Croatia, 379579 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Crown Heights, 379580 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Cuba, 379581 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Czechoslovakia, 379582 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Dalai Lama, 379583 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Democracy, 379584 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Democrats, 379585 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - Dolan, Tony, 379586 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Dole, Robert, 379587 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - Drug Watch, 379588 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - Drugs, 379589
    - 1998-2001, 379590 (Box 26, Folder 21-24)
    - 2002, 379591 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - New York Times, 379592 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Duke, David, 379593 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Egypt, 379594 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Emerson, Steven, 379595 (Box 27, Folder 5)